Well, all our new sprites are in order.
They are just waiting for us to bring them to life.
Now, the first thing we need to do is get the layering right.
The only problem is, scratch only lets you set a sprite to go to the back or front, or go backwards
or forwards a layer.
There isn't an option to have it go to a specific layer.
Currently, what we have been doing is having our sprites go to the front and then go back.
However, while this trick works, if you have 3 or 4 sprites, it causes problems when you have more
than that.
So to set a sprite to a specific layer, what you need to do is first have the sprite go to the back,
then bring it forward.
However, many layers are needed and this is the opposite of how we had it.
So if you look at it, this bottom tree line will be at the highest layer.
So we will bring it forward a six layers.
Then the button will be a layer lower so we can bring it forward five layers.
Then the next set of trees, we will bring forward four layers.
So what that means is that our obstacle tree sprite needs to come forward three layers.
Then our player sprite two layers.
And finally our snow pixel.
Just one layer.
So starting off with the snow sprite, we can go in and change this to go to back.
And then go forward a one layer and do the same for the other sprite, just like that.
Then our player we can say go to back and then go forward two layers.
Our trees also changed to back and we can bring in a go forward and change it to three layers.
Oh, and also I almost forgot.
We also need to set the layer of our score sprite.
So let's drag this script over to it and we can have this go forward four layers just like that.
Now to make our lives easier, we can just drag this code script into each of these new sprites we added.
Just like that.
Then, moving over to our first set of trees, we can have it go forward five layers.
Now for our start button.
We want it to go forward six layers.
And finally our bottom tree line.
We can have it move forward seven layers.
Okay, so that looks pretty good.
Now we need to make it actually work because you will notice if you click the play button.
Well we have a weird merge of our game happening in our start screen.
So our first priority is getting the start sorted out.
And basically what we want is for our game to start when we click this button, meaning this start screen
and trees should hide and our player and obstacles should appear.
Now instead of using an if mouse down and touching sprite like we've done before, we can use this block
here when the sprite is clicked.
Now, when we do click the button, we want to broadcast a message and the message we want is startgame.
So dragging this block when the sprite is clicked over, then the broadcast message.
We can create a new message called Start Game.
Now with that done, let's ensure our other sprites respond.
Firstly, with our background we can disconnect this music from the on flag clicked and rather have
it play with the broadcast message when I receive start game.
This way our ambient sound is always playing, but our music only starts when the game actually starts,
right?
I have a mini challenge for you.
Are you ready?
What we want to happen is for our animation that rotates between these two backgrounds to play when
we click the flag, and then when we click the start button, we want to stop the animation and switch
to the blank backdrop.
Can you make it work?
Here's a tip.
Ideally, you should use functions to create this.
So pause the video and give this a go.
How did you go?
This 1st May be a bit harder than you thought.
So well done.
If you did get it right.
The first things first, we need to create a function.
We will call this background animation.
And here we need to add an input.
And we can call this game start and hit okay.
So now we need to define this function.
So bringing in this classic forever and this if else block then grabbing an equals operator.
And here we can check if game start equals true.
Now if it is we want to switch to our first backdrop.
But if it is not we want our animation to play.
So to do this we can grab two switch backdrops and then stick a wait in between and then a wait at the
end.
Also change it to start screen one and two.
Then all we need to do is grab another.
When flag clicked, bring in this block to call our function and then set the input to false, and then
we can drag another.
When I receive block like so, set it to start game.
Then bring in this function call and set it to true.
But now I've just realized that this doesn't really make sense, because calling background animation
with false starts the animation while calling it with true ends it.
But we'll ignore that oversight for now.
So clicking play.
As you can see, our animation works and clicking start it goes away and our music starts.
Now with that all done, let's move on to our tree sprite.
This one will be a little bit easier.
So firstly dragging in a when flag clicked.
Here we can just show the sprite.
Then dragging in the when I receive block and setting it to start game, we can hide the sprite.
So lastly, we need to create an animation.
Now for this we can just grab a forever loop and a repeat loop inside the repeat loop.
We could have a change X by five and then weight 0.5 seconds.
Then we can just duplicate this, and this time set it to minus five.
And lastly, at the start of our script, let's set the x position to zero and set the y to its current
position.
Now for our other tree sprite.
Because it's the same, we can just drag both these scripts into it like this.
The only thing we do need to do is change the y position.
So here we can just set it to its current position.
So clicking play.
As you can see we have a nice animation with the trees clicking start.
Well they disappear.
Now clearly there is a problem that our sprite and trees are still running.
So let's address that.
Firstly moving to our player sprite, we can just drag in a hide onto this when flag clicked and then
drag in a.
When I receive, set it to start game and then drag in a show block.
And now we can just drag this when our receive block into our tree sprite.
Our snow pixel sprite and our score sprite.
Then first moving to our tree sprite.
Here we can drag the script onto our when our receive start game and stick it onto the when flag clicked.
Then moving to our snow pixel.
We can do the exact same thing here.
So switching that around and moving the hide just like that.
And with the second snow sprite, we can also do the same switch and move.
And lastly, with our score here, we can just drag this setup function call script over to our when
I receive start game like so.
And lastly, you can drag in a hide onto the when flag clicked.
So clicking play.
As you can see that looks pretty good.
And when we click start well there are a few problems.
Anyways, we'll deal with all of this in the next lesson where we'll finish off this game, but I encourage
you to give it a go and try to see if you can fix these final small issues on your own.